<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The barren tree a sermon preached at Pauls crosse October 26. 1623 / by Tho. Adams.</title>
            <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 106.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19979907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19979907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1402:3 or 1719:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The barren tree a sermon preached at Pauls crosse October 26. 1623 / by Tho. Adams.</title>
                  <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug. Matheuues for Iohn Grismand, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Alley, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A4(-A1) B-H4.</note>
                  <note>"Reissued as pt. 2 of STC 115"--STC (2nd ed).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library (New York, N.Y.) and Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIII, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23578:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BARREN TREE. <hi>A</hi> Sermon Preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe <hi>October</hi> 26. 1623.</p>
            <p>BY THO: ADAMS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by AVG: MATHEVVES for IOHN GRISMAND, and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley, at the ſigne of the Gunne. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23578:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23578:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned, Doctor DONNE, Deane of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Prebend-Reſidentiaries of the ſame Church, my very <hi>good Patrons.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot out of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of this Sermons worth, to which I dare not inuite your Iudicious eyes. Nor, any am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to merit of my Patrons, whom I read ſtiled, Petty cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators. But in humble acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement
<pb facs="tcp:23578:3"/>of your fauours, I preſent this ſmall Rent of Thankefulneſſe; the poore fruit of that tree, which growes on your owne ground, and hath not from the world any other ſuſtenance. Vouchſafe, I beſeech you, your Patronage to the child, who haue made the Father of it,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your VVors. deuoted Homager</hi> THO: ADAMS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23578:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Neither affect thoſe Rheumaticke Pennes, that are ſtill dropping vpon the Preſſe: nor thoſe Phlegmaticke ſpirits, that will ſcarſe bee coniur'd into the orbe of employment. But if modeſt forwardneſſe be a fault, I cannot excuſe my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God Almighty, to make a fearefull Comment on this his owne Text, the very ſame day it was preached by his vnworthieſt ſeruant. The argument was but audible in the morning, before night it was viſible. His holy Pen had long ſince written it with inke, now his hand of Iuſtice expounded it in the Characters of bloud, There, was onely a conditionall menace, So it ſhall be: here a terrible remonſtrance, So it is. Sure! He did not meane it for a nine daies won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Their ſudden departure out of the World, muſt not ſo ſuddenly depart from the memorie of the World. Woe to that ſoule that ſhall take ſo ſlight a notice of ſo extraordinary a Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We doe not ſay, They periſhed: Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie forbid it. But this wee ſay, It is a ſigne of Gods fauour, when hee giues a man Law. Wee
<pb facs="tcp:23578:4"/>paſſe no ſentence vpon them, yet let vs take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by them. The Remarkableneſſe would not be neglected; for the Time, the Place, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Number, the Maner. Yet ſtill wee conclude not, This was for the tranſgreſsion of the dead: but this we are ſure of, It is meant for the admonition of the liuing.</p>
            <p>Such is our Bleſſed Sauiours concluſion, vpon a paralel inſtance: <hi>Except ye repent, YE ſhal all LIKEWISE periſh.</hi> There is no place ſafe enough for offenders: but when the Lord is once vp in armes, happy man that can make his owne peace! otherwiſe, in vaine we hope to runne from the Plague, while we carry the Sinne along with vs. Yet will not our wilfull and bewitched Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, from theſe legible Characters, ſpell Gods plaine meaning. No impreſsion can bee made in thoſe hearts, that are ordained to periſh. For their malicious, cauſeleſſe, and vnchriſtian cenſures of vs, God forgiue them: our requitall be onely pitie and prayers for them. Howſoeuer they giue out, (and I will not here examine) that their piety is more then ours: Impudence it ſelfe cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but our Charitie is greater then theirs. Now the holy feare of God keepe vs in the wayes of Faith and Obedience; that the properation of Death may neuer preuent our preparation to die. And yet ſtill, after our beſt endeauour; <hi>From ſudden death good Lord deliuer vs all.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23578:4"/>
            <head>THE BARREN TREE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE. Cap. 13. Verſ. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then ſaid hee to the Dreſſer of his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; Behold, theſe three yeares I come ſeeking fruit on this Fig-tree, and find none: cut it downe, why cumbreth it the ground?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ewes is brought to Chriſt, of a certaine Iudgement, which was not more <hi>Pilates,</hi> then Gods, vpon ſome Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans; who, while they were ſacrificing, were ſacrificed; their blood being mingled with the blood of the beaſts,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23578:5"/>on the ſame altar. Leſt this ſhould be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributed to <hi>Pilates</hi> crueltie, without due reſpect had of the omnipotent Iuſtice, hee ſamples it with another; of eighteene men miſcarrying by the fall of a Tower. No <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> threw downe this, here was no humane Executioner: the matter of their death was morter and ſtones; theſe bad no purpoſe to kill them. This therefore, muſt bee an inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible hand, working by an inſenſible creature: the Iuſtrument may bee diuers, the Iudge is the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Poena paucorum, terror omnium:</hi> as an exhalation drawne from the earth, fired and ſent backe againe to the earth, ſmites onely one place, but terrifieth the whole countrey. So their ruines ſhould be our ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; let them teach vs, that they may not touch vs. They are hitherto but like <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Rodde</hi> turned into a Serpent: not into a Beare or Lyon, leſt it ſhould haue deuoured <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> but into a Serpent, that hee might be more afraid then hurt. It is Gods ſpeciall fauour to vs, that others bee made examples for vs, and not wee made examples for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Nothing could teach them, let them teach vs.</p>
            <p>Of theſe fearefull Inſtances our Sauiour makes this vſe; ſetting downe a peremptory concluſion: <hi>Vel poenitendum, vel pereundum: Except yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23578:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Such vengeance is no way to bee auoyded, but by repentance. But here the Iewes might flatter themſelues; If wee be greater ſinners then they, how comes it to paſſe that wee ſpeed better then they? To this ſilent obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Chriſt makes an Apologicall anſwere, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. You are not ſpared becauſe you are more righteous, but becauſe God to you is more gracious. You deſerue ſuch or ſorer Iudgements; and the reaſon of this impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is not to bee looked for in your inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, but in the Lordes patience: nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not worſe to him, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is better to you: who offers you ſpace and grace to amend, if (at leaſt) at laſt you will bring foorth the fruites of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>There be ſome termes in the Text; (as that the <hi>Vineyard</hi> is the Church, euery Chriſtian a <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> God the <hi>Owner,</hi> euery Paſtor a <hi>Dreſſer:</hi>) wherein your vnderſtandings may well preuent my diſcourſe: theſe known and familiar things I take as granted of all hands.</p>
            <p>It is a Parable, therefore not to bee forced euery way, nor made to warrant a concluſion which the Author neuer meant. This were, when it <hi>offers vs the company a myle, to compell it to goe with vs twaine:</hi> or to make Chriſtes Meſſenger ſpeake our errand. Such is the trade of Rome; what their owne policie hath made neceſſarie, they will teach God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23578:6"/>to make good: this is to picke darkneſſe out of the Sunne. No. <hi>Verificatur in ſenſu ſuo.</hi> like a good creature, it does onely that it was made for. A Parable is not like a Looking-glaſſe, to repreſent all formes and faces: but a well drawne Picture, to remonſtrate that perſon whereof it is a counterfeit. It is like a knife, with the haft it cutts not, with the backe it cuts not, it cuts with the edge. A Candle is made to light vs, not to heate vs: a Stoue is made to heate vs, not to light vs: if this Parable, like the Sunne, may giue both light and heate; the more profitable, the more acceptable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſayd hee to the Dreſſer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That part of it, to which I limit my preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, deliuers it ſelfe to vs in theſe foure paſſages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Conſultation; <hi>Then ſayd hee to the Dreſser of his Vineyard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Complaint. <hi>Behold, theſe three yeeres I come ſeeking fruit on this Fig-tree, and find none.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sentence; <hi>Cut it downe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Reaſon; <hi>Why cumbers it the ground?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſultation. <hi>Then ſaid he vnto, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Dixit, non percuſsit:</hi> hee ſpake, hee ſtroke not: hee might haue ſpared words, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23578:6"/>with wounds. The Tree had rather deſerued the Axe and Fire, then a Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of recouery. How eaſily would man haue reiected his hopeleſſe brother? as when a piece of clay will not worke to his minde, the Potter throwes it away: or wee caſt fouie ragges to the dung-hill, little thinking that they may become white paper. But with God, <hi>Verba antecedunt verbera;</hi> hee will bee heard before hee bee felt. Our firſt Parents, when they had ſinned, <hi>Vocem andiuerunt, Heard the voyce of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.8.</note> Hee reaſoned with them, before he condemned them. If the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers word can correct the child, hee will let the rod alone. Wicked men vſe the ſudden Arguments of ſteele and yron; as <hi>Ioah</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with <hi>Amaſa, in the fift ribbe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.10. 1 Kings 22.24.</note> they ſpeake Daggers poynts. So <hi>Zedekiah</hi> diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Prophet, a word and a blow; yea, a blow without a word: he ſtrucke him firſt, and ſpoke to him afterwards. God deales otherwiſe; <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the doore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>and knocke:</hi> hee knockes at the doore, does not preſently breake it open. Hee giues vs warning of his Iudgements, that gaue him no warning of our ſinnes. Why doeth hee thus? That wee might ſee our miſerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and fall to timely deprecation: that ſo puniſhing our ſelues, wee might ſaue him a labour.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Dixit, non deſtinauit:</hi> as if the Lord would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23578:7"/>double and repeat his thoughts, before hee decreed it to irreuocable ruine. A diuine preſident of moderation! If he that cannot tranſgreſſe in his wrath, nor exceed in his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, will yet <hi>Conſulere amicum,</hi> aduiſe with his friend: how ought fraile man to ſuſpend his furious purpoſes to mature deliberation? It is too common with vs, to attempt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſperate actions, without further counſell then our owne greene thoughts. So Anger is made a Solicitor, Paſsion a Iudge, and Raſhneſſe an Executioner. The wiſe man firſt conſiders, then ſpeakes or does: the mad man firſt ſpeakes or does, and then conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Which driues him on neceſſitie to play the after-game; with ſhame and ſorrow to recouer his former eſtate, or giue it loſt for euer. O holy deliberation, whither art thou fled? <hi>Dauids</hi> Harpe did caſt the euill ſpirit out, this would keepe him from euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in. It is a Porter at the Gate of Gods ſpirituall Temple, Man; that would be as ſure to keepe out his enemies, as <hi>Dauid</hi> would haue bin ready to let in his friends. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſperate precipices of ſin would be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, were this Rule remembred; <hi>Conſule Cultorem?</hi> For matter of eſtate, we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled by the Lawyer: for health of body, aduiſed by the Phyſician: we truſt the Pilot to ſteere our courſe by Sea, the Suruey or to mete out our Land: but for the ſoule let it be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23578:7"/>as barren as this Fig-tree, we take no counſell of the Gardiner. Doe worldlings conſult the Preacher, concerning their vſurious trade before they vndertake it? Doe Gallants ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe with him, before they meet in <hi>Aceldama,</hi> the field of blood? O that they would admit an anſwere from ſuch a friend, before they giue an anſwere to ſuch an enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Dixit Vinitori.</hi> Such is the honour God doth his Miniſters, to acquaint them with his owne purpoſes. <hi>Surely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but he firſt reuealeth it to his ſeruants, the Prophets.</hi> Nothing; which may conduce to the office of their Miniſtery, and the good of his Church.
<note place="margin">Luke 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>To you it is giuen to know the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the kingdome of Heauen. To you,</hi> not to the world, they haue no ſuch reuelation. <hi>It is giuen,</hi> it's none of your inheritance, you were not borne to it. <hi>To knowe Myſteries, Sapere alta,</hi> not common things. <hi>Of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> (not ſecular; ſuch myſteries are for the knowledge of Statizing Ieſuites; but) <hi>of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham the thing that I mean to do?</hi> The matter concerned <hi>Sodome,</hi> not <hi>Abraham:</hi> yet was it reuealed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> not to <hi>Sodome.</hi> But doth God need any mans counſell?
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.34.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath at any time beene his Counſeller?</hi> Will the Potter take aduice of his pots? No; when Chriſt asked <hi>Philip</hi> where ſupply of bread might bee had for the multitude; <hi>This hee ſaid to prooue him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>for he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23578:8"/>himſelfe knew what he would doe.</hi> His queſtions are not his, but our ſatisfactions. Thus doth hee credit his owne Ordinance, teaching the world how to eſteeme of them whom him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo ſingularly honors. How poore a place ſoeuer they finde in mens thoughts, the King of heauen and earth cals them to his counſel. <hi>Priest,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 17.</note> was a title whereof the Princes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were ambitious: they would not, euery man haue written his name on his rod, but in hope that this Dignitie might fall to his lot. Now, is the Miniſtery of the Goſpell inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to that of the Lawe? Was the ſeruice of death more glorious then the ſeruice of life, and ſaluation? If the Euangelicall Couenant bee better, is the Miniſtration worſe? The Sonnes of the great thinke ſcorne of ſuch an imployment: what they held an honor, theſe count a diſparagement: In one and the ſame ſubiect meets their ambition and our ſcorne. It is ill when the <hi>Figge-tree</hi> ſhall deſpiſe the <hi>Dreſſer,</hi> but it would bee farre worſe if the <hi>Dreſſer</hi> ſhould deſpiſe the <hi>Fig-tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>To the Dreſſer.</hi> This is the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of his Miniſters, to whom he hath committed the culture of his Vineyard: all which, by an <hi>Enallage numeri,</hi> are ſumm'd vp in one <hi>Dreſſer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes 4.32.</note> 1. <hi>Quia Cor vnum,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue all one heart.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.12.</note> 2. <hi>Quia offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium vnum;</hi> all their labours meet in that one common terme; the <hi>edification of the Body of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23578:8"/>Chriſt.</hi> 3. It is vſuall to name one <hi>proceteris,</hi> for all the reſt. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>Though I ſhould die with thee, I will not denie thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 26.35.</note> Did <hi>Peter</hi> onely promiſe this? No, but <hi>So ſayd likewiſe the reſt of the Diſciples.</hi> Had not this been a Parable, I neuer found a place of more probable co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for the high Prieſt of Rome to chalenge his vniuerſall Supremacy by. But ſurely, he will neuer <hi>dreſſe</hi> Chriſtes Vineyard, as it ought, vnleſſe in a Parable. Nay, would his Inſtruments forbeare to ſowe it with bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, to manure it with blood, and to caſt <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth</hi> out of his own vineyard, it were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what. But let them paſſe! When the Spirit wrote to a whole Church, he inſcribes his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi> vnder one particular name,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 2. &amp; 3.</note> 
               <hi>Angelo Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi> to the <hi>Angell of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>To the Dreſſer. Dreſsing</hi> implies labour and heedfulneeſſe. I might here touch vpon the Miniſters diligence, that Chriſts Vineyard neuer lie rude and vnpoliſhd through his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault. But this age will looke to that well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: neuer did the Egyptians call ſo faſt vpon the Iſraelites for making of Brickes, as the people call on vs for making of Sermons: &amp; our allowance of materials is much alike. They think it recompenſe bountifull enough to praiſe our paines; as if wee could liue like Camelions, vpon the ſubtill ayre of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations. So they ſerue vs as Carriers do their Horſes; lay heauy burdens vpon their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23578:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:23578:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:23578:10"/>backes, and then hang belles at their eares to make them muſicke. But be our reward little or much, God forbid we ſhould ſlacke <hi>dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> the Vineyard of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>To the Dreſſer.</hi> Why to him? <hi>Vt interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret</hi> that he might pleade for the Tree. So vnwilling is God to deſtroy, that hee would haue vs manacle his hands with our prayers: he would bee intreated to forbeare.
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.7.</note> 
               <hi>Goe thy wayes downe,</hi> for the people which thou broughteſt out of Egypt, <hi>haue corrupted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi> Why this to <hi>Moſes?</hi> That hee might pray for them. He that meant to ſpare them in mercy, meant withall that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould bee beholden to him for that mercie. And <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed chargeth the Lord, ſets vpon him with ſo holy a violence, that as if his prayers could <hi>vincere inuincibilem,</hi> he heares, <hi>Let me alone.</hi> O that euery Vine-dreſſer were full of this gracious affection to the trees vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his charge: yea, who feares God, and in ſome meaſure hath it not? The people forgot <hi>Moſes, Moſes</hi> remembers the people: they could be merry and happy without him, he would not be happy without them. Men robbe vs of our meanes, lode vs with repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: all our reuenge is to ſolicite heauen for them by our ſupplications: they ſue vs, wee ſue for them: they impoueriſh our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall condition, wee pray for their eternall ſaluation. Wee could neuer hope for good
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23578:10"/>to our ſelues, if wee ſhould not returne them this good for their euill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corah</hi> had drawne a multitude to rebell againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16.22.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> pray for their rebels. They were worthy of death, and they had it; yet would theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Leaders haue preuented it: refuſing to buy their owne peace with the loſſe of ſuch enemies. Yea, they are ſo farre from caruing their owne iuſt reuenge, that they would not haue the Lord to reuenge for them. Let vs fill our hearts with this great Example: the people riſe vp againſt their Paſtors, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors fall on their faces for the people. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if God had not meant to heare vs, he would neuer inuite vs to pray. But as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Him to make vs His mouth to you; ſo alſo, your mouth to Him: both to tell you what He doth ſay, and to returne Him what you ſhould ſay; to preach againſt your ſinns; to pray for your ſoules. Doe you heare vs pleade for Chriſt, for Chriſt heares vs plead for you. Indeed, wee are men of polluted lippes and liues: but as Gods power is not ſtraitned through our weakneſſe, ſo, nor is his mercy leſſened through our vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore as <hi>Paul</hi> had his, <hi>Vae mihi ſi non praedicauero;</hi> Woe vnto mee, <hi>if I Preach not:</hi> So <hi>Moſes,</hi> in effect, had his <hi>Vae mihi, ſi non interceſſero,</hi> woe vnto me, <hi>if I pray not: God forbid I ſhould ceaſe praying for you.</hi> But as all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23578:11"/>our Preaching can work no good vpon you, but through the holy Ghoſt: ſo all our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can bring no good to you, but through Ieſus Chriſt. Wee pray for you, forget not you to pray for vs. Indeed, weake ones pray with vs, malicious ones pray againſt vs, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous ones prey vpon vs, fewe pray for vs. We intreat for you, do you intreat for vs; and that onely Mediator betwixt God and man plead for vs all.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Complaint. <hi>Behold I come, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This hath in it two paſſages.</p>
               <p>His
<list>
                     <item>Acceſſe. <hi>Behold, theſe three yeares, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Succeſſe. <hi>I find none.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt, the Acceſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Behold. Ecce</hi> is here a note of complaint. Hee that can thunder downe ſinne with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, raines on it ſhowres of complaint. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Tree;</hi> he might in a moment haue put it paſt beholding, by throwing it into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall furnace. Why doth he complain, that can compell? <hi>Habet in manu potentiam, in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de patientiam:</hi> there is power in his hand, but patience in his heart. To do Iuſtice, we (after a ſort) conſtraine him: but his delight is to be mercifull.</p>
               <p>He <hi>complaines.</hi> All complain of loſt labors: the Shepheard after all his vigilance, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of ſtragling Lambes: the Gardiner after all his diligence, of withering Plants: the Husbandman after all his toyle, of leane
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23578:11"/>Fields, and thin Harueſts: Merchants after many aduentures, of Wrackes and Pyracies: Tradeſmen of bad debtors, and ſcarcitie of monies: Lawyers complaine of few Clients, and Diuines of fewer Conuerts. Thus wee complaine one of another: but God hath iuſt cauſe to complaine of vs all.</p>
               <p>Well, if the Lord complaine of Sinne, let not vs make our ſelues merry with it. Like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> it may make vs ſport for a while, but will at laſt pull downe the houſe vpon our heads.
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The voyce of the Turtle is</hi> (not) <hi>heard in our Land. Vox Turturis, vox gemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> True penitents bee more rare then Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. The voyce of the Sparrow wee heare, chirping luſt: of the Night-bird, buzzing ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: the voyce of the Scriech-owle, croaking blaſphemy: of the Popiniay, gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy pride: the voyce of the Kite and Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, couetouſneſſe and oppreſſion: theſe, and other Birdes of that wing bee common. But, <hi>Non audita eſt vox Turturis:</hi> who mournes for the ſinne of the time, and longs to bee freed from the time of ſinne? It was an vnhappy ſpectacle in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſee at once, <hi>Lachrymantem Dominum,</hi> and <hi>ridentem popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum:</hi> a weeping Sauiour, and deriding ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. We complaine of our croſſes and loſſes, wee complaine of our maladies, of our iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, enemies, miſeries: the Lord open our eyes, and ſoften our hearts, to ſee and feele
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23578:12"/>the cauſe of all, and to complaine of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I come.</hi> The Lord had often ſent before, now he <hi>came</hi> himſelfe; euen by his perſonall preſence, accepting our nature. The Sonne of God that made vs the Sonnes of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Sonne of man, to make vs the Sons of God. Hee <hi>came</hi> voluntarily: we come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, not by our owne wills, but by the will of our parents; Chriſt came by his owne will. He <hi>came</hi> not for his owne benefit, but ours. What profit doth the Sunne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by our looking on him? Wee are the better for his light, not hee for our ſight. A ſhower of raine that waters the earth, gets nothing to it ſelfe; the earth fares the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it. He <hi>came</hi> for our <hi>fruites:</hi> theſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enrich him:
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, our well-doing exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neuer came ſuch an Inhabitant to our Countrey, as <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Had God graunted men the libertie to beg of him what they would, and haue it; they durſt not haue beene ſo bold as to aske his onely Sonne. When the King giues a free conceſſion to his ſubiect, to make choiſe of his owne ſute, without deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; he will not bee ſo impudent as to beg the Prince. Let vs entertaine him well, wee fare the better for him: the profit of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bleſſeth all the reſt vnto vs. Farre bee it from vs to welcome him with ſcandals, with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23578:12"/>blaſphemies, and neglect. Hee may then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, as <hi>Abſolon</hi> to <hi>Huſhai,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Is this thy kindnes to thy friend?</hi> No, you ſay, we make much of him, hold him in the higheſt regard, truſt him with our whole ſaluation. But knowe, Chriſt fares not the better for thy Faith, but for thy Charity. Faith is a beggerly receiuer, Charitie is a rich giuer. Thy Faith is a hand that takes ſomething from him, to enrich thy ſelfe: thy Charitie is a hand that giues ſome thing to him, in his diſtreſſed members. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the ſubiect of all tongues, but he is not the obiect of all hearts. The Schoole diſputes of him, the Pulpit preaches of him, Profeſſion talks of him, Profane men ſweare by him, few loue him, few ſerue him. He is <hi>come,</hi> let him bee made welcome, by ſetting our beſt cheere, and choyceſt fruites before him. Whom ſhould we entertaine, if not our Sauiour?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Seeking.</hi> But, did not Hee know before? What need hee ſeeke, that hath found? Hee that <hi>vnderſtands our thoughts long before</hi> they are borne, cannot be neſcious of our workes when they are done. My anſwere ſhall bee ſhort: the Lords <hi>Quaerit,</hi> is a <hi>Requirit:</hi> hee doth not ſeeke a thing that is hid from him, but requires a debt that is due vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Seeking.</hi> This is no rare, but a continued act. It is not <hi>Veni,</hi> I came: Hee <hi>came vnto his owne, &amp;c.</hi> Nor a <hi>Venturus ſum;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.11.</note> Yet a little
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23578:13"/>while,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> and <hi>I will come.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>S to pulſans, I ſtand knocking:</hi> ſo here, <hi>Venio querens, I come ſeeking.</hi> Hee <hi>ſeekes</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: will you heare how long?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Theſe three yeares:</hi> Much time hath beene ſpent about the Interpretation of this time; how it is appliable to the Iewiſh Synagogue, to whom it was immediatly referred. I find no great difference among Expoſitors, ſauing onely in their tearmes. Some by the firſt yeare vnderſtand the time before the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie; by the ſecond, their returne to Iury; by the laſt, the comming of Chriſt. Some by the firſt yeare, conceiue the Lawe giuen by <hi>Moſes:</hi> By the ſecond, the Propheticall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations: by the third, the grace of our Lord Ieſus. Some reſolue it thus; the firſt yeare was the time of Circumciſion, from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to <hi>Moſes:</hi> the next, the Leuitical Law from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> the laſt is the yeare of Saluation by the <hi>Meſsias.</hi> Others vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the firſt yeare to bee of the Patriarchs, the middle yeare of the Iudges, the third of the Kings. After all this hee was intreated to forbeare it a <hi>fourth</hi> yeare, till it was inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Apoſtles: and then being found fruitleſſe, it was <hi>cut downe</hi> by the Romanes. But I rather take a definite number to be put for an indefinite: <hi>three yeares</hi> is time long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to wait for the proofe of a tree: ſuch a proportionable expectation had the Lord
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23578:13"/>for that Church. If literally you would haue it, I take this to bee the probableſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Theſe <hi>three yeares</hi> were the very three yeares of his Preaching, healing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, caſting out Deuils, working Miracles before their faces. The other yeare which he added, was the time while the Apoſtles offer'd them the Goſpel of ſaluation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the refuſers were <hi>cut downe,</hi> the accepters were ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> He hath likewiſe waited for the Church of Chriſtianity <hi>three yeares;</hi> that is, three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolutions of Ages, thrice fiue hundred yeres. Or he hath tarried the leaſure of the whole world <hi>three yeares:</hi> the firſt yeare, vnder na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the ſecond, vnder the Law: the third, vnder Grace: the fourth is now a paſſing, and who knowes how farre it is ſpent?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Or to apply it to our ſelues, theſe <hi>three yeares</hi> of our viſitation, hath beene ſo many ſcores of yeares. Conceiue the formoſt to be in the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> 6. who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the gold from the ruſt and droſſe of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Ignorance, and Cuſſenage, which it had contracted. The Sunne beganne to ſhine out in his bright luſtre: the Lord <hi>came ſeeking</hi> our fruits; but not finding them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his expectation, nor worthy of the glorious Goſpell: hee drewe another cloud ouer our Sunne: teaching vs better to value that heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> wherewith
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23578:14"/>we were ſo ſuddenly growne wanton. The ſecond yeare, vnder <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> of ſo bleſſed memory: that Royall nurſe, vpon whoſe Boſome the Church of God leaned to take her reſt. Shee did againe vindicate this Vineyard, which had ſo long lyen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Fryars and Monkes, that it had all-moſt quite forgotten the language of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Shee taught it a new to ſpeake the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the Holy Ghoſt. When that Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene was taken from a Crowne of gold to a Diadem of glory, then began our <hi>third yeare;</hi> wherein our preſent Soueraigne was ſent; <hi>Digniſsimus Regno, ſi non natus ad Regnum:</hi> vnder whom we know not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Peace</hi> bee more. Onely let vs bleſſe him, and bleſſe God for him, that we may all be bleſſed in him. Thus farre we may ſay of our Land, as <hi>Syluius</hi> did of <hi>Rhodes; Semper in Sole ſita eſt:</hi> the bright reflection of the Goſpell compaſſeth vs round about. Now he comes this third yeare <hi>ſeeking</hi> our fruites: which when we conſider, wee can ſay no more but <hi>Miſerere Deus;</hi> Lord bee mercifull to vs: for neuer were ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings requited with ſuch vnthankefulneſſe. We condemne the Iewes for abuſing Chriſts patience: God grant they riſe not vp at the laſt day to condemne vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> He comes to a particular man <hi>three yeeres.</hi> 1. In Youth. I haue planted thee in my
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23578:14"/>Vineyard, giuen thee the influence of my mercies; where is thy fruitfulneſſe? Alas, the young man ſends him away, with a <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tempus ficorum:</hi> it is too earely for me to fall to Mortification; would you put me to pennance, before I haue had the leaſure and pleaſure to offend? He is ready to ſend Chriſt away in the Language of that foule Spirit;
<note place="margin">Math. 8.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Art thou come to torment mee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my time?</hi> But whoſe charge is it to <hi>Remember thy Creator, Diebus Iunentutis?</hi> Then the conqueſt is moſt glorious, becauſe then it is moſt difficult. You ſay, It is neuer too late; but I am ſure, It is neuer too ſoone, to be gracious and holy. The Deuill is a falſe Sexton, and ſets backe the clocke of Time in proſperitie: in the day of trouble, hee will make it run faſt enough. 2. In middle age; and now the <hi>buying of Farmes,</hi> and <hi>trying of Beaſts;</hi> the pleaſures of Matrimony, the cares for poſteritie. take vp all the roomes of the ſoule. Men rather buſie themſelues to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fruites of earth, then to yeeld the fruites of heauen. Heere is ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and fulneſſe of ſtature; but ſtill a defect of grace. Perhaps, Chriſt hath now ſome faire promiſes, of fruits heereafter:
<note place="margin">Luke. 9 61</note> 
                  <hi>Let mee firſt go bury my Father, then.</hi> But (a thouſand to one) he finds ſomething <hi>in Domo,</hi> left by his father, that keepes him <hi>a Domino,</hi> from following his Maſter. To preuent this, it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23578:15"/>his caution to the entertained ſeruant; <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thine owne people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and thy fathers houſe:</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgoe and forget thy fathers houſe, then thy Makers ſeruice. 3. In old age: now the decay of body ſhould argue a decay of ſinne. The taſte finds no reliſh in ryot, the eares cannot diſtinguiſh Muſicke, the eies are dimme to pleaſing obiects, very <hi>Deſire failes:</hi> now all things promiſe mortification. Hee that cannot ſtirre abroad in the world, what ſhould he doe but recollect himſelfe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle his thoughts on the world to come? Now fruites, or neuer. Not yet: Moroſitie, Pride, and Auarice, are the three diſeaſes of olde age: men couet moſt, when they haue time to ſpend leaſt: as cheating Tradeſmen then get vp moſt commodities into their hands, when they meane to breake. Still hee <hi>comes ſeeking</hi> fruite, and is returned with a <hi>Non Inuentus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> If yet it weare but as the Prophets <hi>ſigne</hi> to <hi>Hezekiah; This yeare yee ſhall eate ſuch as grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of it ſelfe: and the ſecond yeare ſuch ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the ſame: and in the third yeare yee ſhall ſowe and reape, &amp;c.</hi> the third yeare might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him ſomewhat. But doth hee forbeare all trees thus long? No, ſome are ſnatch'd away in the flower and pride of their life: yea, they bee not fewe, that will not allow themſelues to liue; but with ryot and intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance haſten their owne endes, before they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23578:15"/>haue well begun or learned what life is: like bad Schollers, that ſlubber out their bookes before they haue learned their leſſons. That in ſtead of, <hi>Non eſt fructus,</hi> wee may ſay, <hi>Non eſt ficus,</hi> the tree it ſelfe is gone. And that goodly perſon, which like a faire ſhip hath bene long a building: and was but yeſterday put to ſea, is to day ſunke in the Maine. We doe not eate, drinke, and ſleepe, and take ſuch refections of nature, <hi>vt non moriamur,</hi> that wee might not die; that is impoſſible: but that wee ſhould not dye barren, but beare ſome fruits vp with vs to him that made the Tree.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <hi>Seeking.</hi> It is fit wee ſhould offer our fruits to God, and not put him to ſeeke for his owne. We ſhould be like thoſe <hi>ripe-figs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nath 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that fall into the mouth of the eater.</hi> The beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quours are they that drop from their cells, of their owne accord, without preſſing. The moſt acceptable of all oblations, be the <hi>Free-will-offerings.</hi> Howſoeuer, let vs bee ſure not to diſappoynt the Lord when he <hi>ſeekes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>On this Fig-tree.</hi> It is fit, that hee that plants a Vineyard, ſhould taſte of the Wine: good reaſon,
<note place="margin">Prou. 27.18.</note> his owne tree ſhould yeeld him ſome fruite, conſidering what hee hath done for it he may well challenge it.</p>
               <p n="1">1 He hath planted vs: wee ſpring not vp naturally; as the Oake growes from an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne, the Peach from a ſtone: but a gracious
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23578:16"/>hand hath ſet vs. <hi>We are not borne of fleſh, nor of the will of blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>or of man, but of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Hee hath planted vs in his Vineyard within the encloſed Garden of the Church. Had he left vs to the vnregarded wildernes, without any <hi>Dreſſer</hi> to looke to vs, there might haue been ſome excuſe of our barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The ground that is left to it ſelfe, is (in a manner) blameleſſe, though it be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. But <hi>in Vineaſua,</hi> which he hath fenced in with his prouidence, bleſſed with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing influence, husbanded with his <hi>Dreſſers</hi> diligence, forwarded with the beames of mercy, and ſhowres more precious then the <hi>deawes of Hermon that fell vpon the hill of Sion.</hi> Where wee participate the fatneſſe of the ground, are fed with vnperiſhing Manna, compaſſed about with Songs of deliuerance, and haue <hi>ſeene our deſires vpon</hi> (his and) <hi>our enemies.</hi> Where Righteouſneſſe is our walls, and Peace our bulwarkes, and the wayes bee milke where we ſet our feet.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Wee are <hi>Figtrees:</hi> not brambles, no man expects <hi>Grapes from thornes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.16.</note> Not Okes or Cedars, to be a dwelling for the Storkes: But <hi>Figtrees,</hi> apt for fruit, for pleaſant fruit. If the reſt be fruitleſſe, they ſerue for other purpoſes: but what ſhall become of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren <hi>Figtree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Hee is our Lord, and <hi>Querit ſuum,</hi> he ſeekes but his owne. If our owne Kine giue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23578:16"/>vs no milke, our owne ſheepe afford vs no wooll, our owne land returne vs no encreaſe, we are diſpleaſed: whereas theſe be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creatures; but we haue ſenſe aboue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature, reaſon aboue ſenſe, grace aboue reaſon: We are but tennants of theſe, Chriſt is Lord of vs: our ſinnes bring the curſe of barrenneſſe vpon them, but there is no fault in God, if we be vnfruitfull.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He comes <hi>ſeeking:</hi> not threatning, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, wounding, not felling downe the tree, nor ſtocking it vp by the rootes; but <hi>ſeeking. Dignatur expectare fructus, cui licet eradicare Infructuoſos.</hi> Man is a loſer by the barreneſſe of his garden-tree: were there not a tree left, God is neuer the poorer.</p>
               <p>Now lay all theſe together: a <hi>Lord</hi> that owes vs, wee are his trees: to come into his <hi>Vineyard,</hi> where he may be confident; wee liue on his ground: to looke vpon a <hi>Figtree,</hi> made of an apt diſpoſition to good fruit; ſuch a one as himſelfe hath <hi>planted,</hi> not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually grown vp: a tree <hi>not neglected,</hi> but whereon hee hath beſtowed great care and coſt; <hi>wayting,</hi> not deſtroying: what can we plead for it, if it be fruitleſſe? God is our Lord and Proprietary, England is his Vineyard, euery one of vs his Fig-tree, thus planted, watered, bleſſed by his gracious mercy: Hee comes to vs with patience, that ſhould run to him with penitence: <hi>ſeeking</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:23578:17"/>our fruites, that ſhould make tender of them vnſought; waiting, that might command: now, feare, obedience, and thankefulneſſe, keepe vs from ſending him backe with a <hi>Non inuenio, I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
                  <hi>Fruit.</hi> This is that inſeparable effect that God expects from euery Tree planted in his Garden.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.4.</note> We are <hi>married to Chriſt:</hi> to what ende? <hi>That we ſhould bring forth fruits vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</hi> Hee ſeekes not for leaues, buds, or bloſſomes, but <hi>fruites.</hi> Could leaues content him, wee would not leaue him vnſatisfied: he ſhould haue an Arbour large enough to reach to <hi>the Worlds ende.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 19.4</note> Our tongues runne apace, not ſeldome faſter then our wittes. Wee are Gods debters, and if hee will take our words, ſo: that's all hee is like to haue. Might buds pleaſe him, or bloſſomes: wee haue intentions to good, certaine offers and ſhewes of obedience: which we weare like a cloake, or ſome looſe garment, that when Luſt calls, wee may quickly ſlip off. But when he ſeekes for workes, all our Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants be turned into Mutes, we are <hi>ſpeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse.</hi> O would he aske vs for any thing but <hi>fruites:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 22.12</note> but what ſhould be expected from the <hi>Figtree,</hi> but <hi>Figges?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of euery ſoule here hee ſeekes for <hi>fruites.</hi> Of the Magiſtrate, that he bring foorth the <hi>fruites</hi> of Iuſtice; determining cauſes with ſinceritie of deciſion, and conuenience of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23578:17"/>expedition: being ſo far as equitie permits, a husband to the widdow, and a father to the fatherleſſe. Of the Miniſter, that hee bring forth the <hi>fruits</hi> of knowledge. <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> was his Paſtorall ſtaffe: in one and the ſame night it brought forth buds, and bloſſomes, and <hi>fruit.</hi> Fruitfulneſſe is the beſt argument that God hath called vs: there is not a plant of his ſetting, but the very branches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall flouriſh. I doe not ſay, our paynes ſhall alwayes conuert many Soules; that is Gods <hi>fruite,</hi> not ours: Hee chargeth vs to bee induſtrious in Preaching, let Himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with the worke of ſauing. Of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, he expects the <hi>fruit</hi> of his calling: to bee idle, is to bee barren of good; and to bee barren of good, is to bee pregnant of all euill. <hi>Bella gerant alij, Proteſilaus edit:</hi> but let vs that are called to worke, worke in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; otherwiſe at laſt, wee ſhall make but a ſorry anſwere to that Queſtion, <hi>Vbi fructus?</hi> Let vs all produce the <hi>fruits</hi> of Charity: rich men doe good turnes to themſelues; as they play at Tenniſſe, toſſing the Ball to him that will toſſe it to them againe: ſeldome to the poore, for they are not able to bandy it backe. Pride cuts, and Ryot ſhuffles, but betwixt them both, they deale the poore but a bad game. The <hi>fruite</hi> of Chriſtianitie is Mercie; when the rich, like full eares of Corne, humble themſelues to the poore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23578:18"/>earth in Charitie. Feed him, that feeds you: giue him part of your Temporalls, from whom you expect Eternalls: you cloathe Chriſt with your blackes on earth, hee will clothe you with his glorious whites in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Our mercie to others, is the <hi>Fruite</hi> of Gods mercy to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                  <hi>Fruite.</hi> Nothing is created for it ſelfe, but ſo placed by the moſt wiſe prouidence, that it may conferre ſomething to the publique good; though it be but as the Widowes <hi>two Mites</hi> to the <hi>Treaſurie.</hi> The pooreſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture yeelds ſome <hi>Fruit,</hi> wherein it doth imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the goodneſſe of the Maker. We know not readily, what good Serpents and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine may doe; yet certainly, they haue their <hi>fruit;</hi> both in ſucking vp that poyſon of the earth, which would be contagious to man; in ſetting off the beautie of the better pieces of creation:
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> (for though the ſame hand made both the Angels in heauen, and the wormes on earth; yet the Angels appeare the more glorious being ſo compared) beſides their hidden vertues abſtracted from our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Of ſtones they make yron, rubbiſh ſerues to raiſe Bulwarks, the ſmall pebble for the ſling, wormes and flyes are bayts for Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: euery thing is enabled with ſome gift for the vnniuerſall benefit, and to produce thoſe <hi>fruits</hi> is their naturall worke.</p>
               <p>The Sunne comes foorth of his Chamber
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23578:18"/>like a Bridegrome, freſh and liuely; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth as a Gyant, to runne his diurnall courſe, to lighten vs with his refulgent beames, to generate, cheere, and mature things with his parentall heate: this is his <hi>fruite.</hi> In his abſence the Moone and Starres adorne the Canopie of Heauen, reflecting their operatiue influence to quicken the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer world: this is their <hi>fruites.</hi> The curled cloudes, thoſe bottles of raine, thinne as the liquour they containe, flye vp and downe on the wings of the winde, deliuering their moyſt burdens vpon the earth, teats where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hungry fields and paſtures doe ſucke; yet they expect no harueſt from vs: this is their <hi>fruites.</hi> The ſubtill winds come puffing out of their cauernes, to make artificiall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wholeſome ayres, and nauigable ſeas; yet neither earth, ayre, nor ſea returne them recompence: this is their <hi>fruits.</hi> The earth, in a thankefull imitation of the Heauens, lockes not vp her treaſures within her owne Coffers; but without reſpect of her priuate benefit, is liberall of her allowance, yeelding her fatneſſe and riches to innumerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that hang on her breaſts, and depend vpon her as their common mother for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. Of the beaſts that feed vpon her, Kine giue vs their milke, Sheepe their wooll: euery one payes a tribute to man, their vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fructuary Lord: this is their <hi>fruites.</hi> Fruit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23578:19"/>bearing Trees ſpend not all their ſappe and moiſture vpon themſelues, or the increaſe of their owne magnitudes: but the principall and purer part of it is concocted into ſome pleaſant <hi>Fruites;</hi> whereof they nor their young Springs euer come to taſte; but they proffer it vs, and when it is ripe, they vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily let it fall at their Maſters feete. Neuer did the Oliue annoynt it ſelfe with the owne Oyle, nor the Vine make it ſelfe drunke with the owne Grapes, nor the Tree in my Text, deuoure the owne <hi>Figges:</hi> yet they all ſtriue to abound with <hi>Fruites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me raiſe your Meditations from earth to heauen: the holy Angels there are called <hi>Miniſtring Spirits:</hi> thoſe royall Armies fight for vs againſt our enemies: like Nurſes, they beare vs vp in their armes, and (though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene) doe glorious Offices for vs: this is part of their <hi>fruit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 5.17.</note> The bleſſed Trinitie is alwayes working: <hi>Hitherto my Father wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and I worke.</hi> The Father by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and protection, the Sonne by his mercy and mediation, the Holy Ghoſt by his grace and ſanctification: all diuiding the ſtreames of their goodneſſe, for the beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe of the world. The more any thing furthers the common good, the more noble is the Nature, and more reſembling the Creator.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:23578:19"/>
               <p>The Earth is fruitfull, the Sea, the Ayre, the Heauens are fruitfull; and ſhall not man bring foorth <hi>fruites,</hi> for whom all theſe are fruitfull? While all the Armies of Heauen and Earth are buſied in fructifying; ſhall Man, of more ſingular graces and faculties, be idle, a burden to the world and himſelfe? Both the Church of God for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pietie, and the world it ſelfe for the vpholding of his eſtate, requires our <hi>Fruites.</hi> If Happineſſe conſiſted in doing nothing, God that meant <hi>Adam</hi> ſo happy, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſet him about buſineſſe: but as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe was his Store-houſe, ſo alſo his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe: his pleaſure was his taske. There is no ſtate of man that can priuiledge a folded hand: Our life is, <hi>Vita pulueris, non puluina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> Landes, Meanes, and Moneyes, men make the protections of Idleneſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Adam</hi> commaunded the whole earth, yet worke expected him. In Paradiſe all things did labour for man, now man muſt labour for all things. <hi>Adam</hi> did worke becauſe he was happy, wee his children muſt worke, that wee may bee happy. Heauen is for ioyes, Hell for paines, Earth for labour. God hath three houſes; this is his Worke-houſe, that aboue is his Ware-houſe. O then let vs bee fruitfull; that others benefit may bee ours, our benefit theirs; and the glory of all, the Lords. If Magiſtrates yeeld not the <hi>Fruits</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:23578:20"/>of Iuſtice, Miniſters the <hi>fruits</hi> of knowledge, priuate men the <hi>fruits</hi> of Charitie and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; it is as vnnaturall, as if the Sunne ſhould forget to ſhine, or the earth to fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. God made all theſe for man, hee made man for himſelfe: of vs he lookes for <hi>Fruit,</hi> of vs let him finde it, from vs accept it, in vs increaſe it, and to vs reward it, through Him, in whome alone wee expect mercie, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Succeſſe followes. <hi>Non inuenio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We haue brought the Lord into his <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> heard him calling for the <hi>Dreſſer,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a <hi>Tree,</hi> telling him of a <hi>three yeares</hi> expectation: now, if after all this we inquire for the euent; himſelfe certifies vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>None?</hi> Peraduenture he came before the ſeaſon; <hi>Nondum tempus erat Ficorum.</hi> When ſhould a Tree bring forth fruits, but <hi>Tempore ſuo?</hi> This is the praiſe of the good <hi>Tree,</hi> that it <hi>brings foorth the fruit in due ſeaſon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.3.</note> If the Figge-tree could haue obiected to the Owner,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 5.26</note> as <hi>Eliſha</hi> to his ſeruant; <hi>Hoccine tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus; Is this a time to plant Vineyards, or gather fruit?</hi> Or as the man replyed to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<note place="margin">Luke 11.7.</note> that came to borrowe loaues at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; <hi>Is this a time to lend Bread,</hi> when my ſelfe and family are in bed? The Spring is the ſeaſon of fructifying, the Autumne of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23578:20"/>gathering.
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.12. Iob 38.38.</note> When the <hi>time of the ſinging of Birds is come,</hi> Then <hi>the Figtree puts foorth her greene Figges.</hi> But <hi>Cum fermento perfundatur puluis,</hi> when <hi>the duſt is leauened with myre,</hi> and the <hi>bands of Orion</hi> haue lock'd vp the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Heauen. Who ſeeks fruit in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; hee muſt be content with Winter fruit. There is the Winter of an afflicted Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; no maruell then if neither ripe Figges, nor ſo much as greene leaues appeare: when all the Sappe is retyred to the Roote, as in extreame cold the bloud runnes to the heart to ſuccour it. When the Babylonians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of their captiue Iſraelites ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe Songs, they could ſoone anſwere; <hi>How ſhall wee ſing the Lordes Song in a ſtrange Land?</hi> Is this a time or place to be merry?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.4.</note> But did the Lord come out of ſeaſon? No, hee required it not the firſt day, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but wayted the full time, expecting fruit in the Autumne or Vintage ſeaſon.
<note place="margin">Gloſſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ante tempus querit, qui per triennium venit.</hi> Hee came not with a Trienniall Viſitation, as Epiſcopall Fathers vſe to viſite, once in three yeeres; but euery yeare, euery moneth in the yeare, weeke of the moneth, day of the weeke. Of another <hi>Figge-tree</hi> it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Marke 11.13.</note> that <hi>The time of Figges was not yet,</hi> yet hee <hi>curſed</hi> it: Heere the time was three yeares paſt without fruit, yet he curſed it not. But looke to it; If thou wilt not fructifie <hi>Tempore tuo,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:23578:21"/>thou ſhalt be cut down <hi>tempore non tuo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.17.</note> periſh <hi>before thy time.</hi> There is not a day in the yeare, wherein hee forbeares <hi>ſeeking</hi> our fruit; yet <hi>Venio, non inuenio; I find none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>None? Nunquid quia male quaeſiuit Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus?</hi> Was there any errour in his ſearch? Men often ſeeke <hi>Bona,</hi> good things, <hi>non bene,</hi> not in a good manner. Either they faile in their <hi>Quando,</hi> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſought Chriſt after a <hi>dayes iourney;</hi> whereas hee is too precious to bee miſſed one houre:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.6.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall ſeeke thee Tempore inveniendi, when thou mayeſt be found.</hi> Or in the right <hi>Vbi:</hi> as <hi>Mary</hi> ſought her Son <hi>in Cognatione Carnis, among her kinred;</hi> who was <hi>in Domo Patris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 2.39.</note> in the Temple. So the Papiſts ſeeke now him in Pictures, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bee found in the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Or in their <hi>Quomodo,</hi> as they that ſeeke <hi>aliud pro il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, aliud prae illo,</hi> another inſtead of him, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other beſides him, another with him, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before him, which they doe not ſeeke for him. All theſe ſeeke and miſſe, becauſe they ſeeke amiſſe. The world is commonly miſtaken in their ſearch: <hi>Quaerunt bona locis non ſuis,</hi> they ſeeke for things out of their proper orbes. Men ſeeke Honour in Pride, whereas Honour is to bee found in Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. They ſeeke reputation in bloodie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge; alas, that is to bee found in Patience: <hi>It is the glory of a man to paſſe by an offence.</hi> They ſeeke content in Riches, which is as if
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23578:21"/>one ſhould ſeeke for freſh water in the midſt of the Sea. But in none of theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did this <hi>Seeker</hi> faile: not in the <hi>Vbi,</hi> for he ſought in the Vineyard: not in the <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> for he came in the Vintage: not in the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> for he ſought fruit on that Figtree, about which hee had bene at ſo great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; yet <hi>I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>None?</hi> Haply not ſo thicke with fruites as the <hi>Vines of Engedi:</hi> euery Land is not a Caanan, to flowe with Milke and Honey. But yet ſome competent meaſure, enough to pay the Land-lord rent for the ground it ſtands on; no, <hi>None.</hi> If there bee none to ſpare, whereof the owner may make mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; yet, <hi>Sufficiat ad vſum ſuum, ad eſum ſuum,</hi> that hee may eate the labours of his owne hands; no, <hi>None.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.27. Eſay 6.13</note> If the number bee not <hi>as the Sand,</hi> yet let there bee a <hi>Remnant.</hi> If there cannot bee a whole harueſt, yet let there bee a <hi>Tenth.</hi> If not a Tenth, yet let there bee ſome <hi>gleanings;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich 7.1</note> and that is a woefull ſcarcitie: if the gleanings bee not allowed, yet let there bee heere and there a Figge, a Grape, a Berry,
<note place="margin">Eſay 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>on the outmoſt branches;</hi> that the Planter may haue a taſte: It is too defectiue, when <hi>Non florebit ficus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hab 3.17.</note> the Tree doth not <hi>flouriſh:</hi> but <hi>Quando non erit Vua in vitibus, non ficus in ficulneis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 8.13</note> when there ſhall not bee <hi>a Grape on the Vine, nor a Figge on the Tree;</hi> this is a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:23578:22"/>miſerable ſterilitie. Some thing hath ſome ſauour, but <hi>None</hi> is good for nothing. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede all Trees are not equally loaden: there is the meaſure of a hundred, of ſixtie, of thirtie; an <hi>Omer,</hi> and an <hi>Ephah:</hi> but the Sacred deawes of Heauen, the graces of the Goſpell, bleſſe vs from hauing <hi>None. I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>None?</hi> Peraduenture none ſuch as hee lookes for, no Fruites delicate enough for the Almighties taſte. Indeed, our beſt fruits are neuer perfect and kindly ripened; ſtill they relliſh ſowre and earthly, and ſauour of the Stocke from which they were taken. They are heauenly Plants, but growe in a foraigue and colde Climate, not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, nor worthy the charges and care beſtowed vpon vs. Set Orenge or Figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees in this our cold Countrey, the fruit will not quit the coſt of the planting and maintaining. But the complaint is not here of the imperfection or paucitie of fruites, but of the nullitie; <hi>None.</hi> Some reading that Text with idle eyes; that after all our fruites,
<note place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> wee are ſtill <hi>vnprofitable Trees:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can finde no validitie of merite in their workes, throwe the Plough in the hedge, and make holyday. But ſhall not the Seruant doe his Maſters buſineſſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee cannot earne his Maſters Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Shall the Maſon ſay, I will ſhare
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23578:22"/>with my Soueraigne in his Kingdome, or I will not lay a ſtone in his building? Yet good fruits haue their reward; though not by the merit of the doer, yet by the mercy of the accepter. Sowre they bee of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but in Chriſt they haue their ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and the meaneſt fruite, which that great <hi>Angell of the Conenant</hi> ſhall preſent to his Father,
<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.4</note> with the addition of his owne <hi>precious Incenſe,</hi> are both receiued and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In their owne nature they may bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; but being dyed in the bloud of Chriſt, they are made pleaſing to God. Yea, alſo profitable to the Church, and vſefull to men, ſeeme they neuer ſo poore. Euen a troubled Spring doth often quench a diſtreſſed Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diersthirſt: a ſmal Candle doth good, where the greater Lights bee abſent: and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt fruite of holy Charity, euen a cuppe (though it be not of the iuyce of the grapes out of the Vineyard,
<note place="margin">Math. 10.42.</note> but) of cold water out of the tankard, in the name of Chriſt, ſhall haue the recompence. But heere the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is not of the meannes, or fewneſſe, but of the <hi>Barenneſſe; None</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>None? Euery Tree is knowne by the fruits,</hi> it is Chriſts euerlaſting rule. Howſoeuer the tree liues by the ſappe, and not by the fruits: yet it is knowne to liue by the fruits, and not by the ſappe; for this is hidden. <hi>The iust man liues by his faith,</hi> not by his workes: but he is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23578:23"/>knowne to liue by his works, not by his inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible faith. Neither doth the fruit make good the tree, but the tree makes good the fruit. <hi>Opera bona non faciunt iuſtum, Iuſtus facit bona opera.</hi> Good works make not a man righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the righteous man doth good works. Our perſons are iuſtified before our actions; as of neceſsitie the tree muſt be good, before it can beare good fruit. But how ſhall that tree be diſcerned, that hath no fruit? <hi>I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>None?</hi> Why this to vs? Why ſuch a Text in ſuch a time? Wee abound with fruites: which way can you looke, and not haue your eye full of our workes? They before, in ſuch places, haue ſucceſsiuely commended our fruits. Bee it ſo: yet <hi>Euripides</hi> being queſtion'd why he alwaies made women bad in his Playes, whereas <hi>Sophocles</hi> euer made them good, in his: anſwered, <hi>Sophocles</hi> makes them ſuch as they ought to bee, but I make them ſuch as indeed they are. Their former commendation haue told vs what we ſhould be; but this Embleme, I feare, tels vs truely what wee are. Not all of vs; God forbid: here is but one Fig-tree in a whole Vineyard thus taxed, and farre be it from vs to taxe a whole Vineyard for one barren Fig-tree.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <hi>None?</hi> Yes, enough of ſome fruites, but the Prophet calls them <hi>Ficos valde mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, ſo bad that they cannot be eaten.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iea. 24.8.</note> As the fruite of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23578:23"/>the Vine is commended for <hi>Quickneſſe,</hi> the fruit of the Oliue for <hi>Fatneſſe,</hi> ſo the fruit of the Fig-tree for <hi>Sweetneſſe;</hi> in <hi>Iothams</hi> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.11.</note> But if it beare not <hi>Fructum natiuitatis ſuae,</hi> the fruit of the owne kinde, but bitter figges; here had better be none at all. What an vncomfortable ſight is this to Him, whoſe heart is ſet on his Orchard; after the coſt of ſo deare bloud to purchaſe it, after ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent care to cheeriſh it, and the charges of ſo many workemen to dreſſe it; yea, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much patience to expect it (ſay the Fig-tree does not beare ſo ſoone as it is plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; in our inſancie we can doe nothing, in our minoritie we will doe little, in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: but now it is growne fructifiable) <hi>Iam non guſtare fructus,</hi> not to haue ſo much as a taſte? Yea, were this all; did barrenneſſe onely vſurpe it: but there is worſe then a meere orbitie or abſence of goodneſſe; a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of bitter fruits: <hi>Quaeſiui Vuas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 5.3</note> 
                  <hi>inveni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Labruſcas:</hi> I find <hi>wild Grapes,</hi> luxurient fruits. Inſtead of the hearty effects, which Wine produceth, I am anſwered with the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly preuarications of malice.</p>
               <p>Behold the wonder and ſpectacle of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulneſſe; among all Gods Creatures, Man; and among men the barren Chriſtian. <hi>Though Iſrael play the Harlot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>yet let not Iudah tranſgreſſe.</hi> What may be expected from the wild Forreſt of Paganiſme, when the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23578:24"/>of <hi>Eden</hi> yeelds ſuch fruites? The ſweet fruit of the Spirituall Fig-tree is <hi>mercie:</hi> our God is the God of Loue, our Sauiour is the Prince of Loue, the Church is knit together in Loue: our Roote is Loue, our Sappe is Loue, our Ligaments Loue: now if we ſhall ſucke the bloud one of another, violate the relations of peace, concoct all our moyſture into malice; here is worſe then, <hi>Invenio fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum nullum, I finde none:</hi> for <hi>Invenio fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum malum,</hi> I finde curſed fruits. Wee are growne vnnaturall; the hand ſcratcheth the eye, the mouth biteth the hand: thornes and bryers entwine and embrace one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">Math. 13.27.</note> while (againſt all nature) Fig-trees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure one another. <hi>Lord, thou didſt ſow good ſeed in thy field, whence then hath it Tares?</hi> Here is more fruit then God would haue; but for that he expects, <hi>I finde none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> When wee are filled with his bleſsings, Chriſt lookes for our prayſes; when wee haue <hi>caten</hi> and <hi>are fat,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22, 29. 1 Cor. 10.7.</note> that wee ſhould <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him.</hi> What fruit finds he? <hi>We ſit downe to eat and drinke, and riſe vp to play:</hi> for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, playing. When wee are ſcourged, hee looks for our humiliation and penance; <hi>Sure, in their affliction they will ſeeke me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 26.16.</note> What fruit finds hee?
<note place="margin">Ier. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, thou haſt ſmitten them, but they haue not ſorrowed;</hi> an inſenſible deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. In this caſe let vs pray; Lord, leſſe of the fruits wee haue, and more of them wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:23578:24"/>ſhould haue. <hi>Inſtead of righteouſneſſe, a crye:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 5.7.</note> a cry indeed; a roaring cry of the oppreſſors, and a mourning cry of the oppreſſed. <hi>Haec non ſunt placido ſuſcipienda ſinu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Bells ring, our Chimneis ſmoake, our Fields reioyce, our Children dance, our ſelus ſing and play; <hi>Iouis omnia plena.</hi> But when Righteouſneſſe, hath ſowne, and comes to reape; here is no harueſt; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I finde none.</hi> And as there was neuer leſſe wiſdome in Greece, then in time of the Seuen Wiſe men: ſo neuer leſſe pietie among vs, then now, when vpon good cauſe moſt is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. When the Sunne is brighteſt the Stars be darkeſt: ſo the cleerer our light, the more gloomy our life with the deeds of darkenes. The Cimerians, that liue in a perpetuall miſt, though they deny a Sunne, are not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of impietie, but of ignorance: but <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xogoras;</hi> that ſaw the Sunne, and yet denied it, is not condemned of ignorance, but of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie. Former times were like <hi>Leah, bleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed,</hi> but <hi>fruitfull:</hi> the preſent, like <hi>Rachel, faire,</hi> but <hi>barren.</hi> We giue ſuch acclamation to the Goſpell, that we quite forget to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Law. As vpon ſome ſolemne Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall, the Bells are rung in all ſteeples, but then the Clockes are tyed vp: there is a great vntun'd confuſion and clangor, but no man knowes how the time paſſeth, So in this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall allowance of libertie by the Goſpell,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23578:25"/>which indeed reioyceth our hearts, had we the grace of ſober vſage) the Clocks that tel vs how the time paſſes; Truth and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that ſhew the bounded vſe, and decent forme of things, are tyed vp, and cannot be heard. Still <hi>Fructum non inuenio, I finde no fruits.</hi> I am ſorry to paſſe the Figtree in this plight: but as I finde it, ſo I muſt leaue it, till the Lord mend it. So I come to</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sentence. <hi>Cut it downe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A heauy doome! Alas, will nothing elſe expiate the fault? May not the lopping off ſome ſuperfluities recouer it? Take from the Sinner, the obiect of his vicious error: deface the Harlots beautie, that bewitcheth the Laſciuious: pull the cuppe from the mouth of the Drunkard: Nauſeate the ſtomach of the Ryotous: ſtrip the Popin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iay of her pyed Feathers: ruſt the Gold, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the riches of the Couetous: take away <hi>Macah's gods,</hi> perhaps he will make him no more. If this will not doe, cut off ſome of the armes &amp; branches: weaken his ſtrength, ſicken his body, lay him groaning and blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the bed of ſufferance: griue his heart-ſtrings with the ſenſe and ſorrow of his ſinnes: any thing rather then <hi>Cut it down:</hi> alas no fruit can grow on it then, but ſad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire. A mans houſe is foule, or a little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed; wil he pul it down or rather repaire it?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23578:25"/>
                  <hi>There is hope of a Tree</hi> though the <hi>roote waxe olde in the earth,</hi> and the <hi>ſtock die in the ground;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> yet the <hi>ſprings of water</hi> may put new life into it: but once <hi>cut downe,</hi> all hope is cut down with it. When a man hath taken delight in a Tree, conueniently planted in his garden; what varietie of experiments will he vſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he <hi>cuts it downe?</hi> Alas, thus poore ſilly men, we reaſon: we meaſure things that be vnmeaſurable, by things that be meaſurable, by things that be miſerable. What wee in a fooliſh pitty would doe, we thinke God in his mercifull wiſdome ſhould doe. Yet which of vs wold endure a dead Tree three yeeres together in his Orchard? We would ſay, If it will not beare fruit, to cheere vs; it ſhall make a fire to warme vs. But the Lord hath bene fixe and thirtie Moones gracious in his forbearance, giue him now leaue to bee iuſt in his vengeance. If ſo much indulgence cannot recouer it, there is little hope of it: <hi>Cut it downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> Who muſt doe this? The <hi>dreſſer.</hi> An vnpleaſing office to him, that hath beſtowed ſo much labour vpon it, eſteemed it ſo precious, hoped for ſome reward at his Maſters hand for his diligence about it; now to giue the fatall blow, to <hi>Cut it downe?</hi> And if it muſt fall, let it be <hi>Manu aliena, non ſua,</hi> let anothers hand doe it. <hi>Hagar</hi> will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her dying Sonne; dye he muſt, ſhe was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23578:26"/>perſwaded;
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Modo non videam, Let me not ſee the death of the Childe.</hi> But hee muſt obey; <hi>Arbor non eſt Cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Criſ.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed Parris familias:</hi> the Tree is not the <hi>Dreſſers,</hi> but the Lords; and his owne is at his owne diſpoſing: <hi>Cut it downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> But how? How can the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter be ſaid to cut downe a barren ſoule? Some may conceiue here a reference to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication: Whether the <hi>Greater,</hi> which depriues a man of all benefit by the Churches publike Prayers, and the Societie of Chriſtians.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls, <hi>Tradere Satana, to deliuer vnto Satan:</hi> ſo himſelfe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>Hymencus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering them vnto Satan:</hi> a miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be ſubiected to a ſlaue, to a dogge, a drudge; but then eſpecially fearefull, when God grants vnto Satan a Writ or facultie, <hi>Pro excommunicato cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endo.</hi> The ignominy of ignominy; beſides the perill: For as Chriſt protecteth all the Trees in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; ſo if any be tranſplanted to the wilde deſart, they are vnder the god of this world. Or the <hi>Leſſe;</hi> which is indeed, no other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, then an Act of the Churches Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, whereby ſhe corrects her vnruly chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: that ſmarting with the abſence of wonted comforts, they may be humbled by repentance, and ſo recouer their priſtine ſtate. This cenſure may bee either too cruell,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23578:26"/>or to triuial.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Approued by the Counc. of Trent. Seſſ</hi> 26.</note> The Church of Rome grants Excommunications for things loſt: a man hath loſt his horſe, he may haue an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication againſt him that detaines him: ſo the Father may hap to Excommunicate his owne Sonne, and for the body of a Iade, hazard the ſoule of his Child. Yea, which is worſe, they publiſh Excommunications for ſinnes not yet committed: The Lord of a Mannor hath ſet a rowe of young Elmes, he may haue an Excommunication againſt all thoſe that ſhall do them any harme. This is to hang a man, before he hath done the fact that deferues it. Theſe in rite, forceleſſe, bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare Excommunications, the ridiculous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordments of a mercenary Power, are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thoſe old night ſpels, which blind people had from mungrel Witches, to ſet about their Orchards and Houſes, antidotes and charmes againſt theeuing; wherein diſtruſting the prouidence of God, they made themſelues beholding to the Diuell for ſafetie. Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that would bee paid in their moneys, may procure an Excommunication againſt their Debtors, if they pay not by ſuch a day. This were an excellent proiect for you Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, a rounder courſe then arreſts and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous trialls at Law. But it is to bee doubted, that your Debtors would feare the Popes Parchment leſſe then the Scriueners, and an
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23578:27"/>Excommunication farre leſſe then an Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary. Ther's but foure things exempted from the power of their Excommunication, as <hi>Nauarrus</hi> notes: a Locuſt, an Infidel, the Deuill, and the Pope: ſo he hath marched them, ſo let them goe together. For the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate muſt be a man, a Chriſtian, mortall, and an Inferiour: now the Locuſt is not a man, the Infidell is not a Chriſtian, the Deuill is not mortall, and the Pope hath no Superior. But too much of that; this is a Parable, and heere is no foundation for ſuch a building.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> How? with an Axe of martiall yron? This were an expoſition fit for <hi>Doway,</hi> or the Gunpowder-Enginers: that by <hi>Cutting it downe,</hi> vnderſtood, <hi>Blow it vp:</hi> turning their Axe to a Petarre. Had God ſaid to them, <hi>Cut it downe;</hi> the axe had bin inſtantly heaued vp: yea, they did it, when God ſaid no ſuch thing. Rather then faile of cutting it downe, they would haue ſtockd it vp, roote and all: this is their mercie. But the Spirituall Axe is to cut downe, <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas, non Animas:</hi> when we reade of <hi>cutting downe,</hi> remember it is meant of mens ſinnes, not of their ſoules. Preachers indeed doe wound; but it is <hi>Gladio oris,</hi> not <hi>ore gladij.</hi> with the Sword of the Spirit, not a <hi>Rouillac's</hi> Knife. If God had ment ſuch a <hi>cutting downe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23578:27"/>Nero</hi> had bene a fitter inſtrument then <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> We read, that <hi>their ſound went through the World:</hi> but that their Sword went through the World, we neuer read,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> How then? <hi>Succide,</hi> that is, <hi>Succidendam minare;</hi> threaten that I will cut it downe. <hi>Caſt them out of my ſight; Eijce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 15.1.</note> that is, <hi>Eijciendos pronuncia;</hi> ſay that I will reiect them. <hi>Quod moritur, moriatur:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod ſucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum eſt, ſuccidatur, That which dyeth, let it die.</hi> God ſometimes ſends ſuch farewels and defiances to ſinners that will not repent. <hi>Ephraim is ioyned to Idols, let him alone.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.11</note> If they will not be perſwaded to returne, let them go on to their ruine, let them alone. <hi>If any man will be vniuſt, let him be vniuſt: He that will be filthy, let him be filthy ſtill;</hi> let them periſh. <hi>Abeat, pereat, profundat, perdat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> This was, <hi>Sententia eris,</hi> the ſentence of the mouth: but it may be this was not <hi>Conſilium cordis,</hi> the purpoſe of his heart. <hi>Saepe Deo minante quod peccans meretur, peccanti non fit quod Deus minatur.</hi> Nor can this tax God of leuitie: for he that ſpeakes with condition of repentance, may change his word without ſuſpition of lightneſſe. <hi>Tu muto ſententiam tuam, Deus mutabit ſuam.</hi> Thus was <hi>Niniueh cut downe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug,</note> 
                  <hi>euerſa eſtin ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, vt aedificaretur in bono:</hi> the ſubuerſion was menaced, the conuerſion was intended. The Father ſhuts his rebellions Sonne out of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23578:28"/>doores, will not allow him a lodging, not ſo much as among his ſeruants: yet hee does not meane to let him periſh with hunger and cold in the ſtreetes: but when he hath well ſmarted for his diſobedience, vpon his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubmiſſion he is re-entertained. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>mercies of the wicked are cruell,</hi> but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudgements of God are ſweet. This <hi>Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe,</hi> is <hi>Medicinale,</hi> not <hi>mortale: Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinans, non eradicans:</hi> for reſtitution, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; for remidie not for ruine. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if all this denuntiation and threatning cannot perſwade them to returne, then comes their finall predition: when they haue cut off themſelues impenitently, God will cut them off impartially. But if we turne to deprecation and repentance, he will turne to commiſeration and forgiueneſſe. The Tree is barren, and the Lord ſaies, <hi>Cut it downe:</hi> the Tree fructifies, and he will ſay <hi>Let it ſtand.</hi> O then let vs humble our ſelues, and with ſeaſonable repentance <hi>Cut downe</hi> our ſinnes, that this terrible Sentence may neuer <hi>Cut downe</hi> our ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Reaſon. <hi>Why cumbreth it the ground?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God is an vndependant Lord, and needes not giue a reaſon of his doings: for who can call him to account,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Curita facis?</hi> His Iudgements are not alwaies manifeſt, they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23578:28"/>are alwaies iuſt: nor doth he things becauſe they are good, but they are therefore good becauſe hee doth them. Should hee make ſhort worke on the earth, and diſpatch all barren Trees in a moment: yet <hi>thou continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt holy, O thou worſhip of Iſrael.</hi> If he ſtrickes vs, we are not wronged; it is our deſert, and his Iuſtice. If he ſpares vs, we haue not merited; It is his mercie. <hi>Huic fit miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia, tibi non fit iniuria:</hi> that man receiues mercie, thou haſt no iniurie. Yet that hee might bee iuſtified, and the mouth of all wickedneſſe ſtopped, he is content to giue a reaſon of this ſentence. Thinke not I deale hardly with this Fg-tree; let vs conferre to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and heare one another with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I will ſhew thee ſufficient reaſon of cutting it downe: doe thou ſhew me ſome cauſe why it ſhould ſtand. My reaſon is, <hi>It cumbers the ground. Terram reddit otioſam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utilem.</hi> It is not onely barren <hi>Formaliter,</hi> but <hi>Effectiue.</hi> In a word. 1. It does no good. 2. It doth much harme.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Firſt, It does no good, therefore it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the nouriſhment. <hi>Terra bona,</hi> and <hi>Gens mala;</hi> are an ill match: an opulent Land, and a peſtilent People.
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Peccator non eſt dignus pane quo veſcitur.</hi> The wicked man is not worthy of the bread bee eates, of the water he drinkes, of the ayre he breathes, of the ground hee goes on. The rich thinkes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23578:29"/>himſelfe worthy of delicate viands, coſtly garments: dutifull attendance, <hi>Quia-Diuts,</hi> becauſe he is rich: yet he may not be worthy of a crumme, a rag, a reſpect, <hi>Quia malus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is euill. It will one day grieue ſuch fruitles <hi>Nabals,</hi> when they muſt receiue a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicitie of torments, according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their abuſed benefits, and they wil wiſh that they had not fared ſo well vpon earth, that they might fare leſſe ill in Hell. They liue in the Vineyard, eate the fat, and drinke the ſweet; turning all this iuyce, not into fruitfull cluſters, for the behoofe of Gods ſeruants; but into their owne armes and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: rayſing their Houſes out of the ruines of Gods Houſe. What good doe they? Cut them downe,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Why cumber they the ground?</hi> It is fit, that the <hi>Riches of the ſinner ſhould bee laid vp for the righteous: dentur dignioribus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But if God ſhould at once cut down all the barren Trees among vs, there neuer was ſuch a cry in Egypt, as there would be about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> What innumerable ſwarmes of nothing does beleaguer this Citie? men and women, whoſe whole imployment is, to goe from their beds to the Tap-houſe, then to the Play-houſe, where they make a match for the Brothel-houſe, and from thence to bed againe. To omit thoſe ambulatory Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that weare out the Pauement of this great Temple with their feet, but ſcarſe euer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:23578:29"/>touch ſtone of it with their knees; that are neuer further from God, then when they are neereſt the Church. To omit that rabble of begging and pilfring vagabonds, that like beaſts, know no other end of their creation, but recreation; but to eate, and drinke, and ſleepe. What an armie of theſe might bee muſtred out of our Suburbs? But that Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath diſabled them to any ſeruice: they are neither fit for God nor man. Did they yet but like wormes and inſects, ſpend vp the corruption of the Land, and leaue vs the leſſe, it were ſomewhat. But they are worſe, euen diſeaſes and vnwholſome ayres, to breed infection among vs. Let Authority looke to their caſtigation, or anſwere for their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes: ſo farre as they deſerue, let them not be ſpared; Cut them downe, <hi>Why com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber they the Ground?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The barren Tree doth no good you ſee; but that is not all: It doth much hurt, and that in two reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1 It occupies the roome where a better Tree might grow. The Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you,
<note place="margin">Math. 21.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and giuen to a Nation that will bring forth the Fruites thereof.</hi> A fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Nation would bee content with ſuch a dwelling. Chriſt foretels this mutation. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewes it accompliſhed. <hi>They are broken off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.19</note> 
                  <hi>that we</hi> (in their places) <hi>might be graffed on. Friend, how cammeſt thou in hither,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>not hauing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:23578:30"/>on a wedding garment?</hi> Why doſt thou vſurp the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, where a worthy gueſt might ſit? Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed to purge his Court;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the righteous into the offices of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous. As in caſe of calamitie, the godly are deliuered out of trouble, and the wicked <hi>come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in his roome:</hi> ſo in caſe of felicitie, the vngodly ſhall bee turned out of their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the reighteous ſhall come in their ſtead.</p>
               <p>A Iudge is corrupt; he is girded with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but the girdle ſaggs to that ſide where the purſe hangeth; God will cut him down; here is roome for a good man, that will doe equitie. A Magiſtrate is partiall, and drawes the Sword of Iuſtice in his owne quarrell; which he puts vp in the cauſe of Chriſt: he muſt be cut downe, here is roome for one that will loue and adhere to the truth. An office is abuſed by him that holds it; hee bought deare and hee cannot ſell cheape: it is time he were cut downe; this place will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a man, that will maintaine the place, with vprightneſſe. A Miniſter is barren, hath no milke in his breaſts: <hi>Miniſterium eius accipiat alter;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1.20.</note> Let another take his office; here is roome for one that will feed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. A prophane Patron will let none into the Lords Vineyard, but at the <hi>Non-licet</hi>-Gate; by which good men will neuer enter: his Clarke ſhall be <hi>Simon,</hi> himſelfe will bee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23578:30"/>
                  <hi>Magus:</hi> vengeance ſhall cut him downe; heere is roome for one that will freely put faithfull Labourers into the Viueyard. There growes an Oppreſſor, ſculking in a corner; the nedy cannot finde him, or if they doe, they find no fruit from him; Cut him down, here is roome for one that will pitie the poore. The Lord will roote out ſuch baſtard Plants, and repleniſh his Garden with fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Trees.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 2 It drawes away nouriſhment from bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Plants, that would beare vs fruits. For this Chriſt denounced a woe to thoſe Iewiſh Clarkes, that keeping the Keies of heauen would <hi>neither enter themſelues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 23.13</note> 
                  <hi>nor ſuffer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> What ſhould become of them, that wil neither do good, nor ſuffer good to be done, but cutting downe? A great Oake pines all the vnderwood neere it, yea ſpoiles the graſſe that ſhould feed the cattell.
<note place="margin">Eſay 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> A great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor engroſſeth all round about him, till there bee no place left for a fertile Tree. Meane while, himſelfe hath onely ſome leaues, to ſhaddow his Sychophants; but no fruit, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Bramble-berries, and ſuch as the Hogs will ſcarce eate.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> All couet to be great Trees, fewe to bee good. The Bryar would grow vp to the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Maple, the Maple would be as tall as the Cedar, the Cedar as ſtrong as the Oake: and theſe ſo ſpread their rootes, till
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:23578:31"/>they ſtarue the reſt by an inſenſible foaking. When mother earth, the Church, would deriue her ſap to ſome young hopefull Plant, theſe intercept it. There is maintenance due to the Miniſter, but the barren Impropriator ſtands in his way, &amp; ſucks it al from him: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he leaues him ſome few drops, to coole his temples, but not enough to preſerue life.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> But the famiſhed tree cries againſt him that drawes the life from it, &amp; yeelds no fruit; and God will heare it, <hi>Abſcinde, cut it downe.</hi> How charitable would <hi>Lazarus</hi> haue bene, had he bene owner of <hi>Diues</hi> his eſtate? How would <hi>Mordecai</hi> haue promoted the good of Iſrael, had he bene as great a fauorite as <hi>Haman</hi> was? How freely would the conſcionable man giue ſpiritual preferments, were he a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron? He that feares God, would iuſtly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Church her dues, did he driue ſuch trades, and dwell in ſuch houſes, as you do. But that God, who diſpoſeth all as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, mend all when it pleaſeth him, euen for his owne mercies ſake.</p>
               <p>Thus from a plaine Text I haue deriued you familiar perſwaſions: for I came not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſatisfie the curious head, but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart. Admit but two conſiderations more, and I haue done.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Firſt the Lord hath ſhewed vs the way to be fruitful, by his owne example. He owes vs nothing: if he withold good things, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23578:31"/>chalenge him: if he ſends vs good things, we are bound to thanke him. The laſt yeare, how generall was the complaint all ouer this Kingdome? The Mower could not fill his ſythe, nor the binder vp of ſheues his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. The beaſts periſhed for want of fodder, yea, children dyed in the ſtreet with hunger: the poore Father not being able with all his weekes labour to buy them (onely) bread. The fields were thin, and the barnes thinner: little in many places there was to gather, and the vnſeaſonable weather preuented the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of that little. The emptines of their bowels did iuſtly fill our bowels with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: Famine is a ſore plague. Wee then cryed vnto the Lord for fruits, and he heard vs: Loe in how plentifull a harueſt hee hath anſwered our deſires, to his owne praiſe, and our comfort! Yea, he concluded all with ſongs and triumphs, a ioyfull harueſt-home; the beſt ſheafe of our Wheat, the beſt grape of the Vintage, the beſt flower of our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the beſt fruit of that royall Tree, the ſafe returne of our gracious Prince. Theſe be the fruits of his mercie to vs, where be the fruits of our thankefulneſſe to him?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Secondly, the barren Fig-tree is of all moſt miſerable, and ſo much the more, as it is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in the Vineyard. The Vine fruitleſſe,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 15.3</note> is of all trees moſt vſeleſſe. It is compared to noble and worthy things: to the good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:23578:32"/>
                  <hi>Vxor tua ſicut vitis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 128.3. Iohn 15.1. Iudg. 9.13.</note> to the beſt man, <hi>I am the true vine:</hi> it checres the heart of God and man. But if barren it is good for nothing, not ſo much as to make a pinne to hang a bat on. Oakes and Cedars are good for building, Popplars for Pales, very buſhes for hedging, doted wood for firing: but the fruitleſſe Vine is good for nothing.
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.13.</note> Salt keepes other things from putrefying, but if it ſelfe be putrefyed, what ſhall ſeaſon it? A ſweet Singer delights vs all; but <hi>Quis medebitur cantatori a Serpente percuſſo?</hi> If a Serpent hath ſtung him, who ſhall recouer his voice? If the eye be blind, what ſhall looke to the eye?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad nihilum valet, quod non valet ad finem ſuum.</hi> It is good for nothing, that is not good for the end it was made. If a knife bee not good to cut, we ſay it is good for nothing: yet may ſome other vſe be inuented for it. If a Plough be not good to breake the ground, we ſay it is good for nothing; yet it may ſtop a gap. If a hound be not good to hunt, we ſay he is good for nothing, yet may he in the night giue warning of a theefe. But if a <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> a Profeſſor be not good for fruit, he is indeed, good for nothing. The refuſe of other things haue their vſes: ſowre Wine will make Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, olde Rags make Paper, Lees are for Dyers, Soile is good to fat the Land, Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheards and broken tiles to mend high waies; all good for ſomewhat: yea, they offer to ſel
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23578:32"/>the combings of haires; Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women know whether they be good for any purpoſe or no. But the fruitleſſe vine, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourleſſe Salt, the lightleſſe Lampe, the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Figge-tree, the graceleſſe Chriſtian, is good for nothing.</p>
               <p>We all haue our Stations in the Vineyard, to bring foorth fruits, but what bee thoſe fruits? It was a ſmart Inuention of him, that hauing placed the Emperour, and the <hi>Pope,</hi> reconciled, in their Maieſtick Thrones, he brought the States of the world before them. Firſt comes a Counſeller of State, with this Motto, <hi>I Aduiſe you two:</hi> then a Courtier <hi>I Flatter you three:</hi> then a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, <hi>I Feed you foure,</hi> then a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, <hi>I Couſſen you fiue:</hi> then a Lawyer, <hi>I Robbe you ſixe:</hi> then a Souldier, <hi>I Fight for you ſeuen:</hi> then a Phyſician, <hi>I Kill you eight:</hi> Laſtly a Prieſt, <hi>I abſolue you all nine:</hi> This was his Satyre. But in the feare of God, as our Soueraigne doth gouerne vs in Truth and Peace; So let the Counſeller ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, the Iudge cenſure, the Husbandman la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Merchant trafficke, the Lawyer plead, the Souldier beare armes, the Diuine preach; all bring forth the fruites of righteouſneſſe: that this Kingdome may flouriſh, and bee an exemplary encouragement to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: that our Children may bee bleſſed after vs, our Enemies conuinced, Aliens
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23578:33"/>conuerted, Satan confounded, the Goſpell honoured, the Lord glorified, and our owne ſoules eternally ſaued. Which grace, the happy fruit of the Goſpell; and glory, the happie fruit of Grace; God the Father grant vs all for his mercies ſake, God the Sonne for his merits ſake, God the Holy Ghoſt for his Names ſake: to whom three Perſons, and one moſt glorious God he rendred all honour and obedience, now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:23578:33"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
